<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="hyprland_focus_grab_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2024 outfoxxed
    All rights reserved.

    Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
    modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:

    1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this
       list of conditions and the following disclaimer.

    2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice,
       this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation
       and/or other materials provided with the distribution.

    3. Neither the name of the copyright holder nor the names of its
       contributors may be used to endorse or promote products derived from
       this software without specific prior written permission.

    THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS"
    AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
    IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE
    DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE
    FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL
    DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR
    SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER
    CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY,
    OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE
    OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="limit input focus to a set of surfaces">
    This protocol allows clients to limit input focus to a specific set
    of surfaces and receive a notification when the limiter is removed as
    detailed below.
  </description>

  <interface name="hyprland_focus_grab_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manager for focus grab objects">
      This interface allows a client to create surface grab objects.
    </description>

    <request name="create_grab">
      <description summary="create a focus grab object">
        Create a surface grab object.
      </description>

      <arg name="grab" type="new_id" interface="hyprland_focus_grab_v1"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the focus grab manager">
        Destroy the focus grab manager.
        This doesn't destroy existing focus grab objects.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="hyprland_focus_grab_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="input focus limiter">
      This interface restricts input focus to a specified whitelist of
      surfaces as long as the focus grab object exists and has at least
      one comitted surface.

      Mouse and touch events inside a whitelisted surface will be passed
      to the surface normally, while events outside of a whitelisted surface
      will clear the grab object. Keyboard events will be passed to the client
      and a compositor-picked surface in the whitelist will receive a
      wl_keyboard::enter event if a whitelisted surface is not already entered.

      Upon meeting implementation-defined criteria usually meaning a mouse or
      touch input outside of any whitelisted surfaces, the compositor will
      clear the whitelist, rendering the grab inert and sending the cleared
      event. The same will happen if another focus grab or similar action
      is started at the compositor's discretion.
    </description>

    <request name="add_surface">
      <description summary="add a surface to the focus whitelist">
        Add a surface to the whitelist. Destroying the surface is treated the
        same as an explicit call to remove_surface and duplicate additions are
        ignored.

        Does not take effect until commit is called.
      </description>

      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <request name="remove_surface">
      <description summary="remove a surface from the focus whitelist">
        Remove a surface from the whitelist. Destroying the surface is treated
        the same as an explicit call to this function.

        If the grab was active and the removed surface was entered by the
        keyboard, another surface will be entered on commit.

        Does not take effect until commit is called.
      </description>

      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <request name="commit">
      <description summary="commit the focus whitelist">
        Commit pending changes to the surface whitelist.

        If the list previously had no entries and now has at least one, the grab
        will start. If it previously had entries and now has none, the grab will
        become inert.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the focus grab">
        Destroy the grab object and remove the grab if active.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="cleared">
      <description summary="the focus grab was cleared">
        Sent when an active grab is cancelled by the compositor,
        regardless of cause.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
